Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Winfield Taylor Papers, 1948-1960 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Winfield Taylor papers 1948-1960 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company.
4.7 linear feet Extent: About 2,770 Items
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the largest and oldest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Winfield Taylor worked as a copywriter in the Creative Department of JWT from 1934 until 1960, becoming a Vice President in 1950. The Winfield Taylor Papers span the years 1948-1960 and include correspondence, memoranda, call reports, Review Board minutes, copy, product information, reports, and printed material. Notable correspondents include Joan Didion, Norman H. Strouse, Henry C. Flower, Jr., Samuel Meek, and John Monsarrat. Major clients include Ford, Shell, and Pan American.
RL.00753
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Review Board minutes may not be photocopied.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Winfield Taylor Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1987.
Biographical Note
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the largest and oldest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Winfield Taylor worked as a copywriter in the Creative Department of JWT from 1934 until 1960, becoming a Vice President in 1950. Taylor was born in Wilmette, Illinois. He attended Dartmouth College and, prior to joining JWT, worked at Marshall Field and Company, Henry Hearst and McDonald, McCann-Erickson, and the Curtis Publishing Company.
Collection Overview
The Winfield Taylor Papers span the years 1948-1960 and include correspondence, memoranda, call reports, Review Board minutes, copy, product information, reports, and printed material. Notable correspondents include Joan Didion; Norman H. Strouse; Henry C. Flower, Jr. ;Samuel Meek; andJohn Monsarrat. Major clients includeFord, Shell, and Pan American. Campaigns covered are Worth More...and Why for Ford, and This is the Captain Speaking for Pan American. There are also materials pertaining to the following clients: American Red Cross, Champion Spark Plug, Foundation for Commercial Banks, Institute of Life Insurance, Johns-Manville, Pharmacraft, Charles F. Orvis Company, RCA, Scott Paper, and Standard Brands.
The collection is organized into two series: General Files and Client Files.
The General Files Series includes correspondence and memoranda of a general nature, unassociated with specific clients or advertising campaigns, as well as miscellaneous personal items.
The Client Files Series documents Taylor's work with several clients, with the bulk of materials pertaining to his work for Ford and Shell.
name Headings
Taylor, Winfield; Strouse, Norman H.; Flower, Henry C.; Meek, Samuel W. (Samuel Williams), b. 1895; Monserrat, John, 1912-1995; Didion, Joan; Resor, Stanley Burnet, 1879-1962; Waldo, Ruth; J. Walter Thompson Company; Ford Motor Company; Shell Oil Company; Pan American World Airways, Inc.; American Red Cross; Champion Spark Plug (Company); Institute of Life Insurance (New York, N.Y.); Johns-Manville Corporation; Radio Corporation of America; Scott Paper Company; Standard Brands Incorporated; Advertising agencies -- United States.; Advertising executives.; Advertising copy.; Advertising -- Airlines.; Advertising -- Automobiles -- United States.; Advertising -- Petroleum industry and trade.; Ford automobile -- Marketing.; Marketing.; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Separated Material
The following materials were separated from the collection by the J. Walter Thompson Co. Archives:
Advertisements for Ford, Shell, American Red Cross and Pan American have been relocated to the J. Walter Thompson Company Domestic Advertisements Collection. Cross-reference sheets giving the headline of each advertisement are found in the first folder labeled Copy for each client. Thirteen Ford proof books dating from 1940 to 1957 and 11 Shell proof books dating from 1948 to 1956 have also been placed in the Domestic Advertisements Collection, but may not be cross-referenced within the collection.
Photographs and negatives of Shell's City of Tomorrow advertisement were placed in the J. Walter Thompson Company's Photograph Collection (presently called the Iconographic Collection) in the Clients series. A slide of this advertisement is also available in the Iconographic Collection, Clients Subseries, Slide SF34.
Duplicates of miscellaneous issues of the J. Walter Thompson Company News dating from 1957 to 1959 were discarded. A complete set of this publication for this period may be found in the J. Walter Thompson Company Newsletter Collection.
Two reel-to-reel tape recordings of Ford commercials, circa 1956, were transferred to the J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office. Media Center Audio-Visual Collection in 1982.
Related Material
Materials related to this collection may be found in other J. Walter Thompson Company collections, including the Account Files, Domestic Advertisements Collection, Iconographic Collection, Newsletter Collection, Review Board Records and the Sam Meek Papers.
Contents of Collection
- General Files Series, 1953-1960 and undated, (1 Box)
  Includes correspondence and memoranda of a general nature, unassociated with specific clients or advertising campaigns, as well as miscellaneous personal items.
  - General correspondence and memoranda, 1953-1960 and undated, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Foreign correspondence, 1953, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous personal material, 1960 and undated (Box 1)
- Client Files Series, 1948-1960 and undated [RESTRICTED], 10 Boxes
  Materials document Taylor's work with several clients, with the bulk of materials pertaining to his work for Ford and Shell. Materials include correspondence, memoranda, call reports, Review Board minutes, copy, product information, reports, and printed material.
  The series is arranged into three subseries: Ford, Shell, and Other Clients.
  Note on Restriction: Review Board minutes may not be photocopied.
  - Ford Subseries, 1948-1960 and undated
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1948-1960, (11 folders) (Box 1)
      Arranged chronologically.
    - Call reports, 1957-1960, (10 folders) (Box 2)
    - Minutes: 1958 Model Introduction Meeting, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Minutes: Review Board, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Copy, 1953, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      Includes Worth More and Why--Best Ford Ad for 1953.
    - Copy (1956, 1957 models), 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Copy (1958 model), 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Copy (XK model--Fordet), 1958 (Box 3)
    - Copy (1959 model), 1958-1959, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Copy (1960 model), 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Copy (1961 model), 1960 (Box 3)
    - Songs, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Ideas, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - Advertising plans (1957 model), 1957 (Box 3)
    - Advertising plans (1958 model), 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Model data (1957 model), 1957, (7 folders) (Box 3)
    - Model data (1958 model), 1957-1958, (17 folders) (Box 4)
    - Model data (1959 model), 1958-1959, (9 folders) (Box 5)
    - Model data (1961 model), 1960, (7 folders) (Box 5)
    - Reports: Research Department, 1956-1959, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    - Reports: Production Status, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Foreign models: Britain, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Foreign models: Germany, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Speeches and writings (unknown author), 1956 (Box 6)
    - Promotion campaign (1957 model), 1956-1957 (Box 6)
    - Printed material, 1952-1960
      - Reports: Ford Marketing Research (1957 model), 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - Reports: Ford Marketing Research (1958 model), 1957-1958, (6 folders) (Box 6)
      - Reports: Ford Product Engineering (1958 model), 1957 (Box 6)
      - Model T Instruction Book (reprint), 1954 (Box 7)
      - Advance Advertising Information for FDAF Committees, 1954 (Box 7)
      - Advertising-Merchandising FDAF Digest (Prepared and distributed by JWT Detroit), 1957 (Box 7)
      - The News at a Glance (Prepared and distributed by Field Service Department, JWT Detroit), 1959-1960 (Box 7)
      - Clues to Successful Truck Operators, 1957 (Box 7)
      - The Ford Dealer, 1957 and1959 (Box 7)
      - Ford Times, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
      - Pamphlets for employees, 1957 (Box 7)
      - Ford: All the Facts, 1957 (Box 7)
      - Ford: All the Facts, 1959 (Box 7)
      - 1959 Ford Facts, 1958 (Box 7)
      - Supplement to Used Car Promotional Handbook for Ford Dealers, 1959 (Box 7)
      - Mail promotions, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
      - Automobile and truck brochures (1957 model), 1957 (Box 7)
      - Automobile and truck brochures (1957 model--retractable hardtop), 1957 (Box 7)
      - Automobile and truck brochures (1958 model), 1959 (Box 8)
      - Automobile brochures (1959 model), 1959 (Box 8)
      - Truck brochures (1960 model), 1960 (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1952-1959 (Box 8)
  - Shell Subseries, 1956-1960 and undated
    - Correspondence and memoranda, 1957-1960, (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - Review Board minutes, call reports and notes regarding meetings, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Copy, 1957-1960, (8 folders) (Box 9)
    - Shell Proposition, 1957-1960 (Box 10)
    - Consumer Purchase Panel reports, 1958 (Box 10)
    - Art time schedules, 1957 (Box 10)
    - Estimates, 1957-1958, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Printed material, 1956-1959 and undated
      - Reports, 1956 and1958 (Box 10)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
      - Shell News, 1957 and1959 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous, 1957 and undated (Box 10)
  - Other Clients Subseries, 1953-1960 and undated
    Arranged alphabetically by client name.
    - American Red Cross, 1957
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1957 (Box 11)
      - Copy, 1957 (Box 11)
    - Champion Spark Plug, 1958
      - Copy, 1958 (Box 11)
    - Foundation for Commercial Banks, 1959-1960
      - Copy and memoranda, 1959-1960 (Box 11)
    - Institute of Life Insurance, 1957
      - Copy and memorandum, 1957 (Box 11)
    - Johns-Manville, undated
      - Copy, undated (Box 11)
    - Charles F. Orvis Company, 1957-1958
      - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 11)
      - Copy, 1958 (Box 11)
      - Printed material, 1957-1958 (Box 11)
    - Pan American, 1957-1960
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1957-1958 (Box 11)
      - Copy, 1958-1960, (3 folders) (Box 11)
      - Printed material (Jet clipper service), 1958 and 1960 (Box 11)
    - Pharmacraft, 1959-1960
      - Memorandum and copy, 1959-1960 (Box 11)
    - RCA, 1953 and 1959
      - Copy, 1953 and 1959 (Box 11)
    - Scott Paper Company, 1957 and 1959
      - Correspondence and memoranda, 1957 (Box 11)
      - Copy, 1957 and 1959 (Box 11)
    - Stardard Brands, Inc., 1957, 1959-1960
      - Tender Leaf Tea: Memoranda, 1957 (Box 11)
      - Chase & Sanborn: Correspondence and memorandum, 1959 (Box 11)
      - Chase & Sanborn: Copy, 1959-1960, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous copy, 1957-1959 and undated (Box 11)
Index to Significant Correspondents
Didion, Joan Box 1 (Folder 3)
Flower, Henry C., Jr. Box 1 (Folders 3 and 7)
Meek, Samuel W. Box 11 (Folder 7)
Monsarrat, John Box 11 (Folder 7)
Resor, Stanley B. Box 1 (Folders 1 and 3)
Strouse, Norman H. Box 1 (Folders 1, 2, 3, 7, and 13)
Waldo, Ruth Box 1 (Folder 3)